Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/wolfgangcalicchio-309b438 (LinkedIn) www.wsp.com (Company)

Top Skills

Environmental Awareness Soil Water

Wolfgang Calicchio

Assistant Vice President Senior Chemist at WSP USA Gardiner, Maine, United States

Summary

Consulting analytical chemist specializing in scoping, proposing, costing and establishing analytical laboratory field programs.

Program budgets ranged from several thousand to a million dollars.

Program scopes from several days to three years. Programs have ranged throughout the contiguous United States and Kazakhstan.

Have extensive experience in training and supervising junior chemists. Also have extensive knowledge and experience in various USEPA Region data validation guidelines, and performed and written numerous data validation reports.

Specialties: Specialties include indoor air and vapor intrusion investigations using the Hapsite ER portable GC/MS, applying the TRIAD approach to field investigations, interpreting analytical data results to field investigations, gas chromatography and XRF applications for effective use in SI/FS/RI programs.

Experience

WSP USA E&I, Inc.
Associate Chemist
September 1988 - Present (35 years 3 months)
Portland, Maine Area

As an Associate Chemist, my primary responsibilities include scoping of project requirements, consulting analytical chemist, XRF RSO for the Portland office, cost quotations, performance of required work, training and supervision of technicians, draft and final report writing. Project work has been completed throughout the contiguous United States and Kazakstan.

As a Field Chemist, primary responsibilities include establishing field laboratories, maintaining analytical instrumentation, field analysis of indoor air, soil vapor, soil, marine sediment, soil vapor, and water samples. Methods of analysis include gas chromatography, mass spectroscopy, IR spectroscopy, X-ray fluorescence, and atomic absorption spectrometry.

I began working here when the company was EC Jordan. The company then transitioned to Combustion Engineering, was bought by ABB Environamental Services; sold to Harding Lawson Associates, purchased Law Environmental and became MACTEC, purchased by AMEC and became the part of the Environment and Infrastructure Division. AMEC purchased Foster Wheeler and we became Amec Foster Wheeler, Inc. Amec Foster Wheeler was recently purchased and we are now Wood.

WSP USA

Assistant Vice President Senior Chemist September 1988 - Present (35 years 3 months) Portland, Maine, United States

ABB Environmental chemist 1989 - 1994 (5 years)

Amec Foster Wheeler - Environment & Infrastructure, Inc. Senior Environmental Scientist
September 1988 - September 1988 (1 month)

As a Senior Environmental Scientist, my primary responsibilities include scoping of project requirements, cost quotations, performance of required work, training and supervision of technicians, draft and final report writing. Project work has been completed throughout the contiguous United States and Asia.

As a Field Chemist, primary responsibilities include establishing field laboratories, maintaining analytical instrumentation, field analysis of soil, marine sediment, soil vapor, and water samples. Methods of analysis include gas chromatography, mass spectroscopy, IR spectroscopy, X-ray fluorescence, and atomic absorption spectrometry.

I began working here when the company was EC Jordan. The company then transitioned to Combustion Engineering, was bought by ABB Environamental Services; sold to Harding Lawson Associates, purchased Law Environmental and became MACTEC. Most recently, we have been purchased by AMEC and are now an integral office in the Environment & Infrastructure division.

Peck Laboratories

Chemist

October 1986 - September 1988 (2 years)

Analytical chemist performing biological, inorganic and organic analyses of surfacewaters, groundwaters, marine, sediments, soils, ash. Also scheduled and collected field samples.

Education

University of New England
Bachelor of Science, Marine Biology and Environmental
Analysis · (1982 - 1987)

Martin Luther HS, Maspeth (1980 - 1982)